The month is August 2026,
and you may have noticed that no one
is doing sales
calls anymore. But rewind two years,
and it was the only way
that you could bag a
high-ticket client. So what happened?
Well, in this video,
I'm going to explain the very few rare
scenarios where they
make sense, and where they don't,
why you should potentially give them up.
But there are still people online
proclaiming that you should do them,
and they
disagree with my stance.
And the very simple way to sum this up
is those people
suck at marketing.
Naval Ravikant once famously said,
"You're doing sales
because you failed at marketing,
and you're doing marketing because you
failed at
product." There are a lot of personal
trainers, famous ones with millions of
followers,
who still say you need to get on sales
calls because it's all they know.
It's worked for them,
and it's worked for the people they work
with.
But again,
if your funnel ends with a sales call
and nothing else,
it will only succeed with a sales call
and nothing else.
I'm fortunate to not just have grown one
of the world's biggest coaching apps in
the world. In the last three years,
I've grown a nootropics business to over
$100
million in value.
And even the three "Sunday Times" number
one best-selling books
I've done, you don't get
that title as a "Sunday Times" number one
bestseller of
how good you write. You get
that from how well you sell.
We sold those books through marketing.
For me,
I don't want you to spend all of your time
during the day having to sell to
people when you can be doing a much higher
return thing of marketing.
Even now with this video,
it's pretty crazy for me to talk to a
person
one-on-one to try and win them over
when I could do this video here
and speak to
thousands of people at the same time
and win them over.
But rather than just saying sales calls
are ridiculous and you should never do
them, let's look at some of the pros.
I'm going to steelman the argument.
To anyone that listens to what I say,
I actually don't mind.
I actually recommend sales calls
sometimes.
A video that I did with a one-to-one
student last week, name was Vicky, I
actually gave her a very short funnel.
She said to me she
was overwhelmed by the idea of email
marketing and landing
pages. I go, "Cool.
We don't have to have so many stages in
it.
We can go from socials, content,
straight onto a call."
And in her scenario, I
actually thought it
was a good idea because she was brand new.
And sometimes you're stared down the
barrel of building something
that could take
weeks or months,
or getting people to have a conversation
with you.
And of course, it'd be ridiculous to say,
"No, let's not onboard any new people for
weeks or months." So it
is perfectly plausible to take someone
from socials to
book a call.
There's nothing wrong with that,
but as you're going to find out later
in the video,
you run into certain problems
if that's all you do.
I also agree for certain demographics,
it's very important.
Rewind to Vicky again.
She works with menopausal women.
I don't know menopausal women,
but I can assume
that they may just want to jump on a call
with a woman that's been through what
they've been through.
They can get a real-time sense of empathy
and understanding
and be spoken through what they're doing.
Not to mention menopausal people now,
who are potentially in their 40s and 50s,
may
have been in that slight paradigm shift
between tech-savvy people and my
parents. My mom doesn't even have a phone.
I also think for smaller creators,
say you've only got a few hundred
followers or
maybe even 1,000,
the sales call might be better because you
may not have the
gravitas nor the resources to be paying
for things like a landing page
or a squeeze
page or an email marketing platform.
$99 a month,
that could be a significant chunk of your
revenue.
So for smaller creators in your first six
months of business, there is a time for a
sales call,
but don't even call it a sales call.
Just have a conversation with your
prospect and map out everything
that you would
do for them. Then at the end,
just tell them how much it would cost
and what they
can expect working with you.
It's also very good to explain to someone
with what
you say that there's a money-back
guarantee so they can believe it.
There's also something
that I call the reverse sales call,
which I've spoken about
again before online a few times.
If you have a lead magnet
and you get a lot of
information from people,
you might get their Instagram, their name,
their number,
their job profession, whatever it is.
Let's say I, as a business coach,
I get hundreds of leads a day from YouTube
from
people wanting content critiques.
I could, if I wanted 10 new clients today,
find five people, spend five
minutes and record my screen. "Hi, John,
just got on to your Instagram.
Here are five things
that I would do to fix your business over
the next six months.
Here's a one-time offer.
I'd love to work with you." Out of five of
those, I reckon
three would buy. Now,
considering I charge several thousand
dollars for my
mentorship,
why don't I do 10 of those a day?
Well, because I'm marketing,
so I don't need to sell.
Those clients are going to come through
anyway, and I've automated the entire
system.
That's ultimately what I want for you.
Even if right now that seems daunting,
in a year's time,
if you're going to get the
growth that you want,
you're going to want these systems in
place.
And it's worth noting this as well.
Just because you grow a large audience on
social media does not mean you've nailed
marketing.
You've just got people to follow you.
There are plenty accounts on social media
of personal trainers, of coaches, but
also in other realms where people
are fucking skin.
They got a million followers,
they're skin.
They've got 300,000 followers,
Just because you make funny cooking videos
or react to other videos, that doesn't
mean you make money from it.
Instagram don't pay you for that.
Again, Adam Sullivan,
probably the wealthiest personal trainer
in the world,
one-off,
hasn't even got a million followers.
Whereas a lot of people sometimes look at
the metric of, "Oh, I just got this
person a big audience.
I've done my job." Let's break down the
potential negatives
of doing sales calls,
and we're going to look into two different
areas.
If you do them and
if someone else does them.
The big problem I have with you doing
sales calls, first of all, waste of time.
Even if you're doing three a week,
that's three hours.
If I sat you in a room, this room,
locked the door, turned the camera on
and said,
"Give me three hours of content." In a
year's time,
the compounding effect of three
hours of content or doing the sales calls,
which one do you think is going to
benefit you long term?
It's going to be the content.
Even reading books within your niche
and turning something you've learned in
the
book into a good marketing email.
There are better uses of time than selling
to
people on a one-to-one basis.
Can you imagine building a billboard
that just
advertised to one person on a farm?
It's stupid.
You put a billboard in a busy place.
We have social media.
We have so many ways to get in front of
thousands of people.
To sell to one person is stupid.
And again, if you're selling, you're not
marketing. My next gripe is that
if you've done 20 sales calls,
which isn't a lot,
you should see the recurring themes here
and go, "Okay, the prospect arrives on the
call with this insecurity,
this insecurity.
They want this clarified,
and they want to understand this,
and the guarantee was
the thing that closed them." You can build
something for that.
Have you ever thought about call centers?
Call centers, they have staff
that chat to you on the phone,
and it's down to the
call center to reduce the amount of people
that actually get through to someone to
keep costs down.
Every single step you go through
is a premeditated step to reduce
your likeness of getting through.
"Hey,
if you're looking to change your
insurance, go to the website.
If you're looking to do this,
then head into your local branch."
Speaking to the
person is the last ditch resort,
and it should be for you
and your sales system
too,
because it's very expensive you doing
sales calls.
But not expensive as in money,
expensive in something called opportunity
cost.
If you are giving the time for that call,
you are missing time from
something else. Right now,
I could be doing a sales call for a
high-ticket program.
Instead,
I'm making a video that's going to get me
hundreds of leads and thousands
of views.
It's the highest leverage arbitrage play
here.
But you don't always have to believe me
because I've never done a sales call in my
life.
Mostly because I spent my 20s selling to
people, and I much prefer marketing.
And to distinguish the two again,
I used to work in shopping centers going
up to
people and selling them products like
LoveFilm,
which was between Blockbuster and
Netflix.
I also used to work in door-to-door sales
where I had to sell people into
gas and electric. They already had gas
and electric.
I then found my feet in marketing. Wow,
I could post videos to
the internet, get hundreds of leads,
close dozens of clients, and marketing
is just
so much better than sales. I'll reiterate,
if your funnel only closes with a sales
call,
it will only finish with a sales call.
If all you have is a hammer,
everything you receive will be a nail.
Another consideration, time zone.
If you're operating an online business
or a global business,
which you should want
to, time zones are a problem. If I say,
"Right, I'm caffeinated between 10 and 12.
Every day, that's
when I'm going to do my fucking sales
calls." It's 2:00 in the
UK morning right now.
So that's not going to work.
So people are going to go on to the sales
call, see I can't do it 2:00 a.m.,
bounce,
and you guys aren't getting the data of
the amount of people that bounce
and never come back. So then
if you open your calendar to all time
zones, America,
Australia, whatever,
then there's going to be calls in your
diary all day, which is
just not congruent with work life.
Also, if I arrive and there's loads
and loads of slots, I'm like,
"This person's
fucking not busy, brother.
I'm not going to this. I'm not booking in.
They're obviously part-time.
They've got two clients.
They must be shit." There's an energy
perspective.
Again, if I've got an hour,
why spend it on a call with someone
begging them to
join business when I could be making a
video?
And every time I make a video,
I get better at making a video, which
is compounding
interest of content creation,
compounding interest of chatting to
strangers.
Then there is the deflating feedback.
I sometimes will see one comment
and it'll fucking send me west, and
I'll be like, "You cunt."
And I'll think about murdering the person
and where I'd
bury them, and I get very creative.
I've thought about many places to hide a
dead body.
Only from a creative exercise Yeah,
people are always burying them in parks.
So I used to murder a bloke for being
rude. Don't put him in a public park.
Would you do it in your garden?
Or another time,
I think sometimes out in a pond.
If you've got a deep pond,
go out in a dinghy, a few chains,
and a few bricks.
There are two types of people in the
world,
those that daydream about where to hide
a dead body, and liars. That's a joke.
Relax.
So when you pour your heart out on a sales
call and give everyone the feedback, and
they go, "I need to think about it,"
and they never do think about it, and they
never do get back in touch,
that shit drains.
There are hundreds of people on a daily
basis that reject me, and they see my ads,
they go,
"Fuck off." They see me promote Focus
Pouches and go, "You're a dick."
They see me talk about Manage to Drink,
and they go, "Oh, well, it's too low." I
don't really know about any of them
because I don't know about any of them.
The only things I know
are how many people bought my shit today.
Let me have a look.
I don't even look at this that much,
to be honest, because
sometimes that can put me in a bad mood.
What? I've only made five grand today.
That's a joke. Relax. Five grand.
I made $200 today. That is...
Help. Oh, as far as the week is about,
must be the Australian time zone.
Oh my God, quick,
book in some sales calls. Yeah.
And ultimately,
if someone goes to Calendly
and they see five to 10 slots a week to
do calls, they're going to be like,
"This person's empty." You might not know
what
the problem is with that, but again,
say you go to a pizza restaurant,
it's Friday
night. You go,
"This place looks nice." You walk in,
there's no one in there.
You go, one, it's haunted, two,
the pizza must be shit. How do I know?
Because there's no one in here. There
are negatives if other people do them.
Myself and Sian,
one of my business partners,
he told me I need to bring sales
calls back online.
We brought them back online for the last
few months, and I need
to shut them down. Funnily enough,
actually, thank you.
How come there is no sales call data in
the
deck, please? Have we turned them off?
So what I'm doing is I'm setting up the
team here to ask about the sales call
data.
I know why there's no sales call data,
because it is performing terribly and
they're hiding it from me.
Because I say I hate sales calls,
and they go, "Oh, we
should try them out.
We do this." Here's some reasons why not.
So the first thing is, and by the way,
you can do these if you want.
I'm not your dad. Most closers get 10%.
So on a program that's two or three grand,
that's $200, $300.
If they don't close, they don't get paid.
There's no other way than to have some
form of pressure to convince someone,
"Hey,
Tracy, do you know what?
I've seen many people on these calls,
but not many that
look as amazing as you, Tracy.
And am I right in thinking
that 15 minutes ago, you
said that if you weren't to get in shape,
that you wouldn't fit in the dress that
you wanted to wear to your best friend's
wedding, who you were jealous of since
high school? Well, it sounds to me, Tracy,
that if you don't make that investment,
the repercussions
are you're not going to be happy at what
is the biggest party of
the year. Have I got that right,
Tracy?" They're just thinking about their
10%.
They're not thinking about Tracy.
I hate it. Second thing
is a 10% margin loss.
Imagine this, right?
This bottle of Nutonic creatine and
water is to represent my business.
Within this, the full bottle
is the amount that I charge.
Now, the creatine water within here
is going to be my
costs. So every bottle I earn,
that much is costs, that much is
profit. Now, if I then give a closer
10%, you think it's 10% less money,
but it's not, because the
10% is of the whole amount,
not the profit.
So 10% of the bottle
is probably going to be closer to 25% of
my profit. If I'm giving a closer 10%
and it works out to 25% of my profit,
I'm now earning a quarter less having
someone jump on a phone call.
Now, if I'm earning a quarter less,
that means I'd have to add or work another
day of the week to make the same money.
So giving some stranger 10% of the full
amount, not just
profit,
is equating to a massive amount of your
take-home getting
cannibalized by putting someone else on
the call.
Not to mention no-shows, bad experiences.
I've had comments,
"James booked in for someone with your
team, they didn't even
show up." I'm like, "Great."
That now looks badly on me.
So now I'm making less money.
I look like a cunt.
And if someone gets pressured into fucking
buying something, of which someone did,
by the way, they emailed me. They went,
"Hi, James.
I've had time to think about it.
I don't think I should have bought.
I did a call with the team." I
was mortified.
I was like, "Look,
I'm incredibly sorry that happened.
It's the first time it's ever happened in
my life. I'm just honest with you.
If I had an agenda,
I would not have told you this." Refunded
the person in full,
made sure that the closer didn't get their
10%.
As soon as I finish this call, actually,
I'm going to make sure we are not running
sales calls because we're just not getting
a positive return on it.
And better yet, the team the other day,
they went, "Oh, here's your close rate,
here's your cost per close,
here's your cost per call."
But they did their close
rate as a percentage of calls attended,
not of calls booked.
So it was a close rate of sub 20%. Sub
20%. That doesn't work.
So even those of you that
are mouth breathing, "I love
sales calls. Sales calls
are the best." They're not. They're shit.
And I've done over $5 million in the last
two years without doing them.
And I'm getting rid of them as soon as I
can. So what do you do instead?
You build a page that serves a purpose.
Now,
I'm not saying you can never do a sales
call, but think about this.
Let's say you build out a perfect curated
landing page.
If you want this resource, which is this,
and actually a lot more information, it's
completely free.
I'm going to put a link in the description
for it.
This has helped people increase their
conversions.
And again, the magic thing about this
is if you get this page right,
you can fiddle
with it, and you can A/B split test it.
And I've had it before where people have
changed text, and they've increased their
conversions by 1%. Now,
that doesn't seem like a lot.
But let's say I've got John,
and he's doing a 1% conversion on a
landing page,
which isn't terrible.
Every 100 people that visit the page,
one buys.
Now people go, "Yeah, but on a call,
I get a 10% conversion rate." Yeah,
out of the
people that booked. But there
are probably 1,000 people
that saw the option for a
call and didn't want it. Anyway,
if I take him from 1% to 2%,
he's now making
double the money with no extra work.
So this resource, completely free.
There's going to be a link in the
description for it.
And ultimately, you can send
that to people.
You can optimize the shit out of it.
Even if you are really worried, "Oh,
but what if someone needs a sales call?"
Then you can put an option at the bottom,
"Still not convinced?
Let's have a chat." Because then at least
your river becomes like a delta with
multiple options.
And one of those options can veer off to
the side, and they can
decide whether or not they want to jump on
a call or they want to buy.
Either way,
if you give them a money-back guarantee,
there's no need for a call.
"Hi, James. Interested in your mentorship.
Can we jump on a call to discuss it?" No.
I'm fucking busy, brother.
If I'm going to give anyone 45 minutes of
my time today, it's going to be my
entire fucking following, not you, mate.
No offense,
but if you respect me as a businessman,
you'll appreciate that.
This video right now
that goes on YouTube's going to get cut
up.
It's going to be put on short form.
It's going to get seen by tens of
thousands of
people.
It would be a disservice to my fiancée,
to my son, to my
business partners, to my customers,
to everyone to give you that time.
It's not how I operate a business,
but better yet, sir or madam,
it's not how I
want you to operate your business because
I'm going to make you a stone-cold
fucking killer that doesn't have to beg
people for money on the internet.
Send traffic to a place where people buy.
And if you don't believe me, that
is quite literally what we do for Nutonic.
We send people to a website. "Oh,
do you want to get on a call to talk about
what
flavors?" No. Just fucking buy it.
We do A/B split testing.
We change fonts. We change pictures.
We've got a guy called Joe.
Joe is our website fucking genius.
He moves things around
and increases our conversions.
Our cost per acquisition comes down.
Cost of acquiring a customer comes down.
Average order value goes up by changing an
image.
Imagine taking 4.6% more just by rotating
an image to slightly
different.
I'm not going to tell you what because
there's going to be some CPG
founders watching this. But ultimately,
if your business goes on the trajectory
for
what I want it to, you
are going to have to phase out calls
eventually.
So why not start now? Again,
I've given you the caveats for the people
that don't
need to. Eventually,
you have to give them up,
the sooner the better, because there
is an opportunity cost to every single
time you give someone an hour of your
time.
Whether they say yes or no,
whether you close them
and put the money in the bank,
the opportunity cost is still there.
Resource is in the description.
Click the link below.
If you enjoyed this video,
you're going to absolutely love
this one here.